A Guide to the Papers of Meredith Nicholson
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Meredith Nicholson 1896-1934
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8070
17 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in Special Collections on December 17, 1963 and October 27, 1965. It was made a gift on July 1, 1991.
Scope and Content
Seventeen letters written by Meredith Nicholson, 1896-1934 and n.d. Correspondents include William Gerard Chapman, Douglas Z. Doty, Richard Watson Gilder, Robert Underwood Johnson, Thomas L. Masson, William Henry Rideing, Charles Warren Stoddard, Will Orton Tewson, and Louis Joseph Vance.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - Poem: The Horn, n.d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem: The Horn, n.d.; TMsS, 1 p.
    Same poem with a slight change in the third line.
  - Poem: Mea Culpa, n.d.; AMs, 1 p.
- Letters
  - Meredith Nicholson to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1896 Dec 27; ALS, 1 p.
    Sends two poems to be examined by The Century; includes a previously published poem on Cuba. ]
  - Meredith Nicholson to Robert Underwood Johnson, 1898 Feb 26; ALS, 3 p.
    Returns the "touched up," typewritten version of the poem The Horn, but states that the handwritten variation of it may be more acceptable; mentions the oboe, the Western Association of Writers, a poem regarding the cello, and Richard Watson Gilder. ]
  - Meredith Nicholson to Charles A. Burkhart, 1906 Apr 13; ALS, 3 p.
    Says his busy schedule in Indianadoes not allow him to accept an invitation to a dinner of the Booksellers' Associationin New York. ]
  - Meredith Nicholson to Richard Watson Gilder, 1909 Sep 29; ALS, 1 p.
    Expresses his admiration and appreciation for his Grover Clevelandarticles, especially the many personal things about Cleveland he lets the reader know.
  - Meredith Nicholson to Miss Furnam, 1909 Dec 29; ALS, 2 p.
    Sends a print of his bookplate, done by artist Franklin Booth; mentions that Booth's work can sometimes be seen in Scribner's.]
  - Meredith Nicholson to William Henry Rideing, 1913 Nov 24; ALS, 1 p.
    Regrets being unable to "tackle" A Hoosier Boyhood this winter; says he will try to fit it in the spring.
  - Meredith Nicholson to William Henry Rideing, 1914 Mar 7; ALS, 1 p.
    Follow-up letter; promises to have something on A Hoosier Boyhood by April 15.
  - Meredith Nicholson to Douglas Z. Doty, 1914 Oct 24; ALS, 1 p.
    Replies to suggestion of a serial of his next novel in The Century, saying he has already been given an option on it; hopes to have something to offer in the future.
  - Meredith Nicholson to Thomas L. Masson, 1920 Oct 15; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    Promises to send a "little piece" for Life.
  - Meredith Nicholson to Will Orton Tewson, 1925 Jan 27; ALS, 2 p.
    Regrets not being able to do the second volume of These U. S.; tells of his and gubernatorial candidate Carl's defeat in the November elections in which Nicholson ran for State Senator, and makes some sarcastic remarks on the state of things in the Hoosier Commonwealth, the Ku Klux Klan, and Catholicism.
  - Meredith Nicholson to Will Orton Tewson, 1926 Apr 10; ALS, 1 p.
    Says that time does not allow him to review the "Jackson book," but he recommends Professor Bassett of Smith College for the job.
  - Meredith Nicholson to [Louis Joseph] Vance, 1927 Mar 9; ALS, 1 p.
    Refers briefly to World War I and The Port; expresses satisfaction that a copy of The House of a Thousand Candles was found in one of the trenches.
  - Meredith Nicholson, Asuncion, Chile, to William Gerard Chapman, 1934 Oct 18; TLS, 1 p.
    Writes during service as a United Statesminister, referring to "A Reversible Santa Claus."]
  - Meredith Nicholson to Charles Warren Stoddard, [his uncle], n.d.; ALS, 2 p.
    Reports about his upcoming voyage, September 7, on the "Friesland," Red Star Line; hope to find a letter from his uncle aboard ship and to get a new book by Stoddard for Christmas.